Levi Stewart Udall collection, 1842-1974
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Levi Stewart Udall collection, 1842-1974
MS 293
Udall, Levi Stewart
Papers, 1842-1974 (bulk 1910-1960), of Levi Stewart Udall (1891-1960), lawyer and judge. Includes personal files, correspondence, reminiscences, activity files, ledgers, and speeches relating mainly to his family, their settlement in Saint Johns, Arizona, his professional activities and services to the state and the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints.
2.5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Levi S. Udall was born 20 January 1891 at Saint Johns, Arizona, to David K. and Ella Udall, Morman pioneers to Arizona in 1880. His childhood was spent working on his father's farm and carrying United States mail by team and buckboard for his father's mail contract business. He attended public school in St. Johns, completed his secondary education at Gila Academy (1910-1911), and briefly attended the University of Arizona, Tucson.
He married Louise Lee of Thatcher, Arizona, on 10 June 1914. They had six children: Inez, Elma, Stewart, Morris, Eloise, and Burr. In addition to the farm, the family operated Apache Abstract Company (c. 1930-1945), the only title company in Apche County. He was member of the Arizona Boy Scouts Councils (1915-1960). He worked as a clerk for the Apache County Board of Supervisors (1915-1918), and as a clerk for the Superior Court (1919-1920). An Democratic National Convention in San Francisco (1920). Admitted to the state bar (1922), he served as county attorney for Apache County (1922-1923, 1927-1928). He was elected as Judge of the Superior Court (1931-1946), and later, as Judge to the Arizona Supreme Court (1947-1960).
He was appointed Ward president for the Young Men's Mutual Improvement Association (1915-1920), a Morman organization. Ordained into the Mormon priesthood by his father, David K. Udall in 1920, Levi Udall was a committed member of his church. He served as president of the St. Johns Stake (1922-1945), and later was appointed as Patriarch for the Phoenix North Stake.
Dedicated to the preservation of his father's deeds, he edited a biogrpahy prepared by his sister, Pearl Udall Nelson, titled Arizona Pioneer Mormon (1915). A member of many civic associations, he was awarded both the Medallion of Merit (1959) and an honorary Doctor of LAws (1960) by the University of Arizona.
He died of a heart attack in Wickenburg, Arizona, on 30 May 1960.
Organization
This collection is organized into seven series:
Series I: Personal Files, 1842-1974
Series II: Correspondence, 1909-1962
Series III: Reminiscences, 1903-1956
Series IV: Activity Files, 1937-1962
Series V: Ledgers, 1932-1959
Series VI: Speeches, 1920-1960
Series VII: Miscellaneous Printed Matter, 1918-1969
Scope and Content Note
Papers, 1842-1974 (bulk 1910-1960), of Levi Stewart Udall (1891-1960), lawyer and judge. Includes personal files, correspondence, reminiscences, activity files, ledgers, and speeches relating mainly to his family, their settlement in Saint Johns, Arizona, his professional activities and services to the state and the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints.
The bulk of these papers are found in three series, Correspondence, Activity Files, and Speeches. These papers best document the Udall family, their settlement in Arizona, the influence of the church in their lives, the editing and publication of his father's memoirs in Arizona Pioneer Mormon, and the many civic and religious speeches given by Levi Udall.
This collection does not document Udall's official tenure as a leader in Mormon organizations, or his career as a lawyer and judge in St. Johns and Phoenix. There is little information which recounts his youth on the farm, his stewardship as farmer, or his life as father to six children, including two of Arizona's most respected Democratic politicians. There is little correspondence between members of the Udall family.
Access Terms
Udall, Levi Stewart, 1891-1960 -- Archives
Udall, David King, 1851-1938
Udall, Louise Lee, 1893-1974
Ross, Harry D.
Nelson, Pearl Udall
Udall Family
Graham-Tewksbury Feud
Mormons -- Arizona -- History
World War, 1939-45 -- Personal narratives
Judges -- Arizona
Apache County (Ariz.) -- History
Saint Johns (Ariz.) -- History
Correspondence
Speeches
Container List
- Series I: Personal Files. 1842-1974
  Contains resumes, diplomas, lists of court cases highlighting his career, and biographical information relating to Levi and Louise Udall. Includes two booklets recalling the lives of Levi and Louise Udall, and five audio tapes of a tribute to Levi Udall, "This is your life," and the funeral services for Levi, and later, Louise L. Udall.
  - Personal Files: Biographical. 1915-1960 (Box 1)
  - Personal Files: Biographical. 1915-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal Files: Biographical. 1915-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personal Files: Certificates and Diplomas. 1904-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Personal Files: Memorial booklets and audiotapes. 1959-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1909-1962
  Family correspondence is largely letters received by Levi Udall during the 1950s and to which he stapled his outgoing replies. Selected subjects covered are church activities, experiences in the armed forces during World War Two, family reunions and vacations, and birthday and holiday greetings. Of interest are letters from David K. and Ella Udall to Levi which discuss David's work for the church in Mesa, Arizona, travels to Utah, and other routine family matters in the 1920s and 1930s. A selected index of correspondence follows.
  The general correspondence addresses a wide variety of topics relating to Levi Udall's professional, religious, and civic interests. There is correspondence from lawyers, law professors, and judges discussing various court cases, invitations to speaking engagements and fund-raisers, congratulatory notes, letters of appreciation, and matters relating to the Mormon Church in Arizona.
  - Udall family. 1918-1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Udall family. 1918-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - David K. and Eliza Luella Udall. 1923-1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Pearl, Joseph, Joseph Jr. Nelson. 1909-1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General. 1921-1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General. 1921-1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General. 1921-1959 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General. 1921-1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - General. 1921-1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - General. 1921-1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series III: Reminiscences, 1903-1956
  Contains texts relating to the history of a Mormon womens' relief society by Ella Udall; a brief history by Levi Udall on the construction of the Apache County Court House; memories by Pearl Nelson of the family's stay in Hunt and St. Johns in the early 1900s, early Mormon history in Arizona and her research notes on Don Lorenzo Hubbell and Arizona history; a typescript copy of recollections by Osmer D. Flake concerning the Pleasant Valley War of the mid-1880s; and a typescript copy of Orland K. Hamblin's service in the U.S. Army from 1941-45 including his narration of the Japanese invasion of the Philippine Islands, the "death march" to Bataan, his life as a prisoner of war from 1942-45, and his liberation and return to the United States.
  - General. 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - On the Mormon women's relief society. 1842-1903, ca. 1903 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - History and cost of Apache County Court House. ca. 1918 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Early memories of the Hunt-St. Johns period of our lives, and other research notes. 1931-1933 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Some reminiscences of the Pleasant Valley War and the causes that led up to it. ca. 1937 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - My experiences in the service and as a prisoner of war of the Japs. 1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Activity Files, 1937-1962
  Contains mostly correspondence relating to the settlement of the estates of David K. and Ella Udall, and later, Levi Udall; a case file relating to one of Levi Udall's most noted trials Arizona vs. Southern Pacific Railroad; a folder pertaining to his activities as a leader of Boy Scouts in Arizona; mateials relating to his election campaigns for the judgship of Arizona Supreme Court; files relating to the publication, distribution, and reviews of Arizona Pioneer Mormon; and his Doctor of Laws honorary award from the University of Arizona.
  - Condolences on deaths of David and Ella Udall. 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - David K. Udall Estate: Correspondence. 1938-1944 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - David K. Udall Estate: Correspondence. 1938-1944 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Arizona vs. Southern Pacific. 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 10a)
  - Arizona vs. Southern Pacific. 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 10b)
  - Arizona Boy Scouts 1943-1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Arizona Supreme Court Election files. 1946-1958 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Arizona Supreme Court Election files. 1946-1958 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Arizona Supreme Court Election files. 1946-1958 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Arizona Supreme Court notes and summaries. ca. 1950s (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Arizona Pioneer Mormon: Correspondence. 1926, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Arizona Pioneer Mormon: Correspondence. 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Arizona Pioneer Mormon: Correspondence. 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Arizona Pioneer Mormon:Pedigree chart and notes. ca. 1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Arizona Pioneer Mormon:Book reviews. 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Doctor of Laws. 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Levi S. Udall Estate. 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series V: Ledgers. 1932-1959
  Contains two volumes relating to accounts for Levi Udall's farming, title service, and real-estate ventures; his election campaign of 1946; the settlement of David K. Udall's estate; and miscellaneous family loans. Indexes to the ledgers are found inside front covers.
  - Ledgers. 1932-1959 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Ledgers. 1932-1959 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series VI: Speeches. 1920-1960
  Contains public addresses and research materials, mostly periodical clippings, given by Levi Udall. There are two other speeches, one by H.D. Ross relating to the history of the office of the Arizona Supreme Court, and the other by Dr. Clarence G. Salsbury relating to political, social, and economic problems of the Navajo Indians. The bulk of this series, which constitutes nearly half of the entire collection, consists of speeches by Udall on occasions of patriotic and religious holidays. There are also a number of funeral talks revealing the accomplishments of pioneers and citizens of Apache County; graduation speeches to local high schools and colleges; professional addresses to associations of lawyers and judges; and talks given to Mormon church groups concerning its history and teachings.
  - Dedicatory remarks: Arizona Supreme Court Building. 1939 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Navajo Problem. 1948 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - General. 1920-1958 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - General. 1920-1958 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - General. 1920-1958 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - General. 1920-1958 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - General. 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - General. 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Christmas. 1945-1959 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Easter. 1936-1954 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Funeral. 1940-1960 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Funeral. 1940-1960 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Funeral. 1940-1960 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Graduation. 1929-1960 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Graduation: fragments. 1929-1960 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Latter-Day Saints. ca. 1920-1960 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Latter-Day Saints. ca. 1920-1960 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Latter-Day Saints. ca. 1920-1960 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Latter-Day Saints. ca. 1920-1960 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Series VII: Miscellaneous Printed Matter. c. 1918-1969
  Contains clippings, poems, and brochures collected by and/or about Levi Udall and the family. Includes an Arizona Superior Court Final Decree involving water rights on the Little Colorado River in the St. Johns Irrigation Company vs. Round Valley Water Storage and Ditch Company, et al, 1918; and a history of telegraphy in Utah which was compiled by Kate Carter in 1961.
  - Clippings. c. 1940s-1950s (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Poems. c. 1930s-1940s (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Printed Materials. c. 1918-1969 (Box 5, Folder 8)